# **GUILHERME DA ROSA**

guid.rosa@gmail.com - https://github.com/guilhermedr https://www.linkedin.com/in/guilherme-da-rosa/

+55 48 991166528 - Brazil

#### PERSONAL STATEMENT

My job is to solve problems related to data pipeline, data transformation, and data migrations. My career started in 2008 when my first approach to data was through the QA (Testing) area. From the beginning, I have worked in IT areas such as business analysis and development coordination. My involvement with data and databases has always been strong. I'm that person who extracts data, transforms data, and uses data in different scenarios in my professional life. Languages such as SQL, PL/SQL, and scripts to manipulate data (any kind), has been part of my career since the beginning.

# **SKILLS AND PROFICIENCIES**

Relational database, SQL development, PL/SQL, ETL/ELT, scripts for any data purposes, and Rest APIs. Good knowledge with Spark, Databricks, Data Lake, Delta Lake, Azure Data Factory, Jupyter Notebooks, Python for data analysis, and BI tools. Requirements management, gathering and documentation producer. Strong ability to understand problems and provide solutions. Strong knowledge in software development life-cycle (SDLC).

#### **EXPERIENCE**

Data Dev Lead and Migration Analyst | CSM - Central de Software Municipal | Brazil 10/202

10/2020 - present

Helping the Data and Migration team to deliver solutions to resolve data problems.

- Data Migration
- Data Integration
- Data Extraction for multipurpose (reports, legal documents, business intelligence)

# **Software Development Coordinator | Betha Sistemas Ltd | Brazil**

04/2020 - 09/2020

Helping the Data and Migration team to deliver solutions to resolve data problems.

- Data Migration;
- Data Extraction for multipurpose.

**Data Migration Analyst** | Independent Consultant for Betha Sistemas' Partners | London 03/2019 - 03/2020

Helping companies from Brazil to:

- Customizing and building rules required for business requirements;
- Managing and executing projects to migrate data between systems in cloud technology;
- Modeling applications for ERP and Accountancy control.

#### Achievements

- Built process to adapt and load data in cloud systems (API method), keeping the data consistency;
- Built scripts and reports required;
- Migrated data from legacy platform to new platform (SAAS, API Method);
- Built tools to help deploy new clients in a few steps.

# Helping to:

- Gather and manager requirements for new cloud products;
- Look after backlog improving requirements continuously;
- Do sprint planning and release planning meetings;
- Build functional requirements, non-functional requirements and business rules;
- Provide support in the last level of customer service for other levels before.
- Develop a data migration pipeline from legacy systems to new cloud systems.

#### **Achievements**

- Helped to build new application in legacy system that solved problems existed over than 5 years;
- Redesigned a lot of scripts and reports resulting in a decrease time to issue them;
- Had trained PM to do the CPRE-FL exam (Certified Professional for Requirements Engineering) of IREB resulting in 80% of approving at the exam;
- Had become a specialist in government accounting department of the biggest state of Brazil that has over than 10 million (BRL) annual revenue;
- Created the data migration pipeline from legacy systems to new cloud systems.

# Software QA | Betha Sistemas Ltd | Brazil

Data Science - MBA LIGTL - XP Group | Brazil

10/2008 - 12/2010

2022

- Create and maintenance test cases, write test plans and define test strategies for desktop system;
- Train new testers on business rules, company process, software features and test techniques;
- Distribute tasks to the team members and make estimates about task execution time.

## Achievements

- Built scripts to guarantee quality on the regression tests;
- Helped to build a checklist with required points that need to be checked when release a new system version.

## **EDUCATION & QUALIFICATIONS**

Data Ocience - MIDA   1011 - XI Group   Brazil	2022
Bachelor Degree in Information Systems   ESUCRI- College of Criciúma   Brazil	2013
Technician in industrial informatics   SATC   Brazil	2007
PROFESSIONAL DEVELOPMENT	
Azure Databricks & Spark Core For Data Engineers(Python/SQL)   Udemy	2022
Bootcamp Data Science   IGTI Bootcamp	2022
Intermediate Level English Course   Escape Campus LTD	2019
Data Science Fundamental I   Udacity	2017
CPRE-FL Certified   IdentifierCredential ID 16-CPRE-FL-00057-BR	2016

## **LANGUAGES**

Portuguese | Native English | Advanced